Finding Aid of the UW-Milwaukee Roberto Hernandez Center Records, 1970-2008
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
UW-Milwaukee Roberto Hernandez Center Records, 1970-2008
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee. Roberto Hernandez Center
UWM Archival Collection 116
3.0 cubic ft. (6 boxes) 14 digital files (1 MB)
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
Records and publications from the Roberto Hernandez Center and its predecessor, the Spanish Speaking Outreach Institute. This collection consists mainly of correspondence from the advisory committee, reports, meeting minutes, and publications including newsletters and brochures. These records document staff and budget issues, community programs, program evaluations, and statistics and special problems of Hispanic students at the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee. Also included are records from the UWM Hispanic Council, which worked on issues affecting Latinx students and staff across the university.
Renamed as the Roberto Hernandez Center in 1999, the Spanish Speaking Outreach Institute was founded in 1970 with the purpose of increasing the enrollment of Hispanic students at the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee, and providing services related to education for Milwaukee's Hispanic community. Initially established within the Office of the Chancellor, the Institute later became part of the College of Letters & Science. The Center offers English classes, helps students receive financial aid, tutors incoming UWM freshmen, and provides counseling and information services. It also supports Hispanic art exhibits and theater productions, speakers, and community awareness activities.
Directors of the Institute
1970-1972 Armando Orellano, Acting
1972-1974 Rafael A. Gutierrez
1974-1975 Gregorio Montoto, Acting
1975-1978 Arnold C. Vento
1978-1983 Rodolfo J. Cortina
1984-1989 Santiago Daydi-Tolson
1989-1999 Felipe Rodriguez
Directors of the Roberto Hernandez Center
1999-2002 William Velez
2002-2016 Enrique Figueroa
2016- Alberto Maldonado (interim)
Records of the UWM Roberto Hernandez Center and its predecessor, the UWM Spanish-Speaking Outreach Institute. The majority of the collection consists of administrative files of the Center, including meeting minutes, correspondence with university units and community groups, program reviews and reports, and files on projects run by the Center. A smaller, but significant, portion of the collections consists of publications from or supported by the Center, including a number of research projects headed by faculty affiliated with the center and production notes for a video on Puerto Rican literature. The collection also includes records of the Hispanic Council, an oversight and advisory group that addressed issues for Latinx students across campus. Of particular interest in this portion of the collection is a 1995-1996 survey of Latinx students at UWM, which provides data on the effectiveness of retention initiatives and on self-identity issues in the Latinx community at UWM.
The files are organized alphabetically by folder heading, then chronologically.
Related Material in the UWM Libraries
Tony Baez Papers Milwaukee Manuscript Collection 8
UW-Milwaukee College of Letters & Science Records UWM Archival Collection 1
UW-Milwaukee Student Affairs, Office of the Assistant Chancellor Records UWM Archival Collection 58
An inventory of the digital files in the collection is available in the archives.
Administrative/Restriction Information
There are no access restrictions on the materials, and the collection is open to all members of the public in accordance with state law.
An unknown donor transferred the collection to the Archives prior to 1989. Center Director Enrique Figueroa transferred additional materials to the Archives in January 2007 (accession 2006-034). The Department of Sociology transferred additional materials to the Archives in 2011 (accession 2011-024)
As of November 22, 2016, all electronic files were accessible on a Intel Core i5-4570 CPU (3.20 GHz, 4 GB RAM) running Windows 7 Enterprise, with Service Pack 1. Windows Picture and Fax Viewer and Adobe Acrobat were used to access the files.
The collection includes records in the following file formats:
Microsoft PowerPoint Presentation 97-2003 [.ppt]
Microsoft Word Document 6.0 and 97-2003 [.doc]
Microsoft Excel 97 Workbook [.xls]
Plain Text [.txt]
WordPerfect for MS-DOS/Windows Document [.wpd]
Contents List
- UWM. Roberto Hernandez Center Records, 1970-2008, UWM AC 116; 3.0 cubic ft. (6 boxes) 14 digital files (1 MB)
  - 15th Anniversary Celebration Committee, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Activities, Sponsored and Co-Sponsored, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Administrative Files, 1995-2001 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Advising, 1976-1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Advisory Committee
    - Correspondence and Memos, 1970-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Meetings and Minutes, 1985-1995 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Members Lists, 1978-1995 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Notes, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Proposal, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Recommendations, 1988-1995 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Reports, 1985-1988 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Student Affairs Sub-committee, 1985-1988 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Sub-committee, Council for the Education of Latin Americans, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Sub-committee for Awards, Report, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Yearly Report, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Alcoholic Beverage Drinking Practices of Hispanic College Students, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Minority Leadership Conference, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Articles/Press Releases, National Endowment for the Humanities Grant, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Black/Hispanic Forum, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Brochures and Publications, 1973-1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Budget, 1984-1996 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Chicano Films, List, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Chicano Literature
    - Articles/Published Materials, circa 1981 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Bibliography/Author Directory, circa 1981 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - First Film Outlines, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Interviews with Chicano Writers, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Release Forms and Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Scripts, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Scripts, Villareal Tape, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Colloquium, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Colloquium Report, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence
    - 1972, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - 1980-1984 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1985-1991 (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
  - Counselor Information Workshop, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Curandismo: The Science of Folk Healing in the Mexican-American Culture, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Data, Notes, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - "Design for Diversity", UWM Annual M/D Report, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Director's Report to the Advisory Committee, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Directory of Agencies and Organizations for the Spanish Speaking in Wisconsin, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Evaluation, Five-Year Review of Minority Program Offices, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Evaluation Reports, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Founding Documents, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Goals and Objectives, 1970-1995 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Hispanic Artists in Wisconsin, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hispanic Arts in the Park, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Hispanic Council
    - 1980-2005 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Clippings, 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, 1988-1994 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1988-1994 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Race and Ethics Research Instruments, 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Hispanic Ethnic Studies, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Hispanic Ethnic Studies TV Series, Closing Credits, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Hispanic Ethnic Studies TV Series, Set Design and Costumes, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Hispanic Freshmen, Studies and Statistics, 1981-1989 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Hispanic Issues, General, 1970-1982 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Hispanic Migration: Historic Glimpses, Notes and Outlines, circa 1981 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Hispanic Migration: Historic Glimpses, Tape Logs, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Hispanic Minority Ethnic Studies, Television Lecture Series: A Videotape Bank, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Hispanic Policy Development Project, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Hispanic Students Academic Services, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Hispanic Students Academic Services, Report, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - "How the College Views the SSOI", Report from Dean, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - International Seminar for Minority Students, Proposal, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Latin Awareness Week, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Latinos in the Midwest Research Symposium, Research Materials, 1999-2001(
  - Linguistics Symposium, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lost in the Big Campus: Hispanic Students at the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Luis Valdez: Notes on an American Theatre in Process, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mission Statements and History, 1999-2008
  - Newsletters, 1975-1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Nosotros...We...", U.S. Department of Commerce, Booklet 4, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Organizational Charts, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Peer Mentor, Reports, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Photo Essay on Wisconsin Hispanic Women, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Planning Document, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Program History, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Programs, Miscellaneous, 1975-1985 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Publications
    - Chicano Pinto Research Project: A Model for Chicano Drug Use and Effective Utilization of Employment and Training Resources by Barrio Addicts and Ex-Offenders, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Directory of Agencies and Organizations for the Spanish Speaking in Wisconsin, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - El Mutualista
      - Index of Names, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Introduction, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Master Copy, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - In the Barrio: Survival and Success, Drafts, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Institute Paper Series: The Puerto Rican Community of Milwaukee, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Introduction to the Chicano Novel, Marvin A. Lewis, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Pamphlet, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Revista Chicano-Riquena, 1977-1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Revista Chicano-Riquena, "Puerto-Rican Literature: A Landscape of the Seventies, Essay, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - The Hispanic Culture Family, A Puerto Rican Perspective, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Puerto Rican Literature
    - Photographs and Notes, circa 1979 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Release Forms, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Scripts, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Video Tape, Production Notes, Includes Music Lyrics and Poetry, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Puerto Rican Parade Committee, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Recruitment and Retention Activities, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Report on First Semester Freshmen Dropouts, 1983-1984 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Second Language and Second Dialect Acquisition, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Spanish/Portuguese Joint Positions, Correspondence and Related Documents, 1970-1982 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Spanish Speaking Outreach Institute
    - 1987-1998 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Advisory Committee, 1985-2000 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Bulletins and Reports, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Staff Meetings, 1978-1986 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Summary Reports, 1984-1999 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Summer Education Program in Puerto Rico, 1981-1984 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "The Take-Over of the Chancery", William Quiles, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Transfer to Department of Student Affairs, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Tutoring Program, Report, 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Velez, William Research Files, 1999-2000
  - Victor Hernandez and La Salsa de Dios Report, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Visual Arts Video, Notes and Related Documents, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Visual Arts Video, Tape Logs, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Wisconsin Conference on the Hispanic Family, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Working Plan, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 19)